[wind blowing]
[indistinct chatter]
[engine powering up]
[indistinct chatter continues]
[woman] Okay, okay.
[laughs]
Eight times!
Pretty accurate.
You should be used to it by now.
[woman laughs]
[man, on TV] But rather
than pay a fair price
for our precious deuterium,
the UNSC leadership on Reach
seek to enslave us.
New deal.
Yeah, let someone else deal.
The Professor has sticky hands.
You saying I cheat?
I'm saying you don't
wash your hands.
My hands are filthy with
the blood UNSC marines.
Speech, Professor.
Regale us with another one
of your war stories.
[Professor]
I've got scars older than you.
-The things I've...
-"...things I've seen."
[man, on TV]
They've repeatedly sent legions
of marines and their
super weapons, the Spartans,
to crush us.
But war need not be the answer.
And that is why Jin Ha
has sent me
and trusts me to negotiate
an end to this endless war.
Turn that shite off.
As the Bard once wrote,
"Wise--"
Vinsher's a fool,
but he's a dangerous fool,
giving people false hope.
His peace talks will fail,
and the UNSC will come at us
with everything they've got.
You mark me.
You mean Spartans?
[laughter]
Have you seen a Spartan
up close?
I've faced marines.
[laughter]
"I've faced marines."
One Spartan is worth
a hundred marines.
[Professor]
Ah, but, Djanka,
there's another difference
between Spartans and marines.
Mm?
Marines can be killed.
Spartans aren't human.
They're faster,
stronger, smarter.
They cannot be stopped.
They just keep on killing...
without mercy...
till there's nothing left...
to kill.
You in or out?
[laughter]
Jin Ha!
Tell our young one here.
The General knows.
Either Madrigal is free,
or it's not.
There's no middle ground.
[man]
Aw, come on!
Oh, you got to be kidding me.
Unbelievable.
Everything okay,
General?
Where's my daughter?
Probably out wandering...
with her friends.
You know Kwan.
-[Cara] Slow down!
-[groans]
I didn't sign up for this!
[panting and groaning]
I am completely shanked.
This better be worth it, Kwan.
[Kwan] Less talking,
more looking, Cara.
[Cara] Look, if the General
finds out we left the outpost--
[Kwan] What my father
doesn't know won't kill him.
[laughs]
I told you I'd find it.
Madrigal, the galaxy's highest
concentration of heavy hydrogen.
Power your ships...
and power your drugs.
This is why you have to stay,
Kwan, to find shit like this!
[Kwan]
Too bad for you,
soon as I find a way,
I'm getting off
this stupid rock.
[Cara]
Where will you even go, Kwan?
The UNSC owns the galaxy.
[Esso]
She's not gonna leave.
She'd miss us too much.
Doubters first.
-[Cara] Yes!
-[Faaz] Yeah.
See you on the other side.
[all chuckle]
[soft, distant rush]
[Cara]
Kwan, where are you going?
-[Neru] Off to plot her escape.
-[all chuckle]
[Cara]
How long before this kicks in?
[Neru] My brother says
it's pretty quick.
[indistinct chatter]
[distant laughter]
[Cara]
Guys! Wait...!
[distant laughter]
[rumble]
[explosive rumbling]
[distant laughter]
[lively chatter]
[Cara] Knew you would
come to play!
[Neru]
Hey, your face is glowing!
[Kwan breathing heavily]
[Esso]
Kwan, where have you been?
[Kwan] We need to get back
to the outpost.
-Why? What's going on?
-There's a ship out there.
-UNSC?
-I don't think so.
Neru, no, I'm serious!
Come on, Faaz!
[Faaz]
Kwan...
[explosion]
[Kwan screams]
-Esso!
-[all screaming]
[explosions]
[panicked shouting]
[gunfire]
[flare whistles]
[distant shouting]
[distant man] I don't know. They
should have been here by now.
Kwan Ha.
Red flare!
Flag General Ha!
-[overlapping chatter]
-General Ha!
Red flare,
north of the outpost!
[Klaxon blares]
Seal the pipes!
Get your weapons!
[indistinct shouts]
[engine revving]
[overlapping shouting]
Spread out!
[all shouting]
[panting]
[screams]
[indistinct shouts]
Stay low! Stay low! Stay low!
Stay down!
[man]
Right behind you.
-[man] Here!
-[guns cock]
[man 2] In position!
[Klaxon blares]
[overlapping shouts]
Kill the alarm!
Stand by!
[man]
Move out! Move out!
Move out!
[Jin Ha, in Korean]
Papa! Papa!
[both speaking Korean]
[explosion]
[soldiers scream]
[in English]
Do your job!
Get in the line!
Malchin!
Come, come, this way.
Go inside the pipes.
[man]
Inside! Inside!
Get on in, get on in!
[man 2]
Move it, move it!
Come on! Come on!
Quick! Quick! Quick!
Go, go, go!
[panting]
[girl whimpers]
[man]
Be ready.
[wind blowing]
[gunfire]
[all scream and gasp]
[heavy footfalls]
[in Korean]
[snarling]
[shouting in Korean]
[gunfire]
[shouting in alien language]
[gunfire continues]
What are those things?
I don't know
what they are.
[screaming and shouting
continue]
[breathing heavily]
[grunts in alien language]
Papa!
[man]
Go!
[groans]
[panting]
-Where are you going?
-I have to go. I have to help.
Are we gonna die?
No, of course not.
We're warriors,
aren't we?
-Yeah.
-Stay put. I'll be back, okay?
[shouting
in alien language]
[woman]
Take cover!
[mutters in Korean]
-[gunfire]
-[screams]
[screams]
-Let me in! Let me in!
-[pounding on door]
-[roars]
-[screams]
-[[blades retract]
-[creature snarls]
[panting and grunting]
Kwanya!
[all scream]
[speaking alien language]
[yells]
Go! Go! Go!
How many are there?
-Kwan!
-I don't know,
but they have a ship.
Holy Mother of God,
it's all true.
What? What's true?
I thought it was UNSC
propaganda.
[shouting]
[snarls]
[man]
A ship!
UNSC!
[woman]
Take cover!
[Professor]
Oh, shit!
The Spartans.
Spartans!
Silver team, engage.
Taking over watch.
[indistinct shouts]
[men screaming]
[in alien language]
[alien snarls]
They're helping.
The Spartans are helping!
I never thought
I'd see the day.
-They're on our side now.
-[Professor] So they are.
So let's fight!
[Kwan yelps]
[panting]
Clearing north quadrant.
[snarls]
[sharp cry]
[shrieks]
[grunts]
[roars]
[screams]
[explosions]
[Riz] Elite cluster,
west quadrant.
[sharp grunt]
[loud blast]
[panting]
[men screaming]
[creature snarling]
[roars]
[explosions]
[breathing heavily]
[snarls]
[gasping]
[gunshot]
[panting]
[gasps]
[John] Silver team,
clear the perimeter.
[screams]
[snarling in alien language]
Team, I need covering fire.
South quadrant.
[alarm beeping]
[beeping continues]
[John]
Kai, hold your position.
Any time now.
[motor whirrs]
[sizzling]
[breathing heavily]
Papa?
Kwanya.
[heavy footfalls]
No! No!
No!
[gasps]
[cries softly]
Link Command, Silver team.
Covenant forces on planet
Madrigal neutralized.
Twenty Elite warriors killed,
150 civilians.
No survivors.
[Kwan]Wait!
[John]
Correction: one survivor.
Female. Juvenile.
Silver team commencing
comprehensive search of the area
for enemy landing site.
Wait! Don't just leave!
[sobbing]
Papa!
[opening theme music plays]
[flames crackling]
[soft sobs]
[whimpering softly]
Chief.
Covenant Phantom.
[John]
Vannak, Riz, clear that ship.
[Vannak]
Hey, Chief.
Kai, on me.
Master Chief 1-1-7
reporting on
the planet Madrigal.
We found the Covenant ship.
Local grid 12-Tango-Zone-Echo.
Now investigating the interior
of a nearby cave.
Assessment report.
Covenant excavation.
[Riz] Cave network
does not appear
to be a natural formation.
Observing debris consistent
with plasma cutters.
Covenant forces
appear to be excavating
for some kind of object.
Unclear as to its nature.
[snarling]
Retrieving now.
[energy flows]
[massive energy flow]
[birds tweeting]
[muffled chatter and laughter]
[John's father]
Don't go too far.
[Riz]
Chief!
[breathing heavily]
[Kai]
Chief, sitrep?
[growls]
-[gunshots]
-[John] Riz, Vannak,
one Elite approaching
cave entrance.
[soft gasp]
[thud]
[Kai]
Master Chief?
You three commandeer
the other ship.
Take it back to Fleetcom
for research and intel.
I'll retrieve the object
and follow in the Condor.
I'll fly with you.
No. Go with the others.
That's not procedure.
Go with the others.
That's an order.
Roger that.
[footsteps recede]
[sighs]
[Halsey] Security access,
Dr. Catherine Halsey.
Open Spartan mission logs:
Madrigal,
Master Chief 1-1-7.
[John, on monitor] Alien forces
appear to be excavating
for some kind of object.
Unclear as to its nature.
Retrieving now.
[computerized voice]
Admiral Parangosky:
Access granted.
A hundred and fifty
dead civilians in Madrigal
is not a good look
for your Spartans, Catherine,
even if they were rebels.
The Covenant wiped out
an entire rebel garrison
before Silver team
could intervene.
We saved one.
1-1-7's bringing her in.
One survivor's not going
to make my job any easier.
The security committee's
looking for an excuse
to cut your funding.
John recovered something
on Madrigal.
Possibly Covenant.
-We'll add it to our collection.
-No, no, no, no.
This...
this is different.
It's like nothing
I've ever seen.
We've been fighting
these alien creatures for years,
and we still have no idea what
they want, where to find them,
or how to beat them.
Command on Earth
want answers.
If that object can tell us
anything about them,
I have a feeling the committee's
concern about dead rebels
will go away.
One more thing.
They want a friendly face
talking to the survivor.
Miranda Keyes
knows Madrigal.
I've asked her
to do the reach-out.
Is that going to be an issue?
No, no, no.
But the Madrigal object
comes straight to my lab
for first analysis
upon arrival.
Alien tech
is Miranda's division.
John found it.
It belongs here.
[soft sigh]
[equipment powers up]
[equipment pulses
and whirrs]
I told you
that was a nonstarter.
We have paused
active development.
You've paused nothing.
Catherine, your genius
has given us
so much to be thankful for.
Channel that genius
appropriately and legally.
Get rid of that,
and any others.
-Clear?
-Clear.
I've given you a long lead,
Doctor.
Don't hang me with it.
[door beeps open]
[door slides closed]
[in alien language]
[Makee]
[panting]
Hey.
Anybody! Please!
Please!
Hey. Hey, you!
[Kwan shouting indistinctly]
[muffled]
Hey! Open the door!
Please!
-Open the door!
-[woman] Kwan.
How are you feeling?
Who are you?
I'm Miranda Keyes.
I'm talking to you from
the UNSC headquarters on Reach.
So sorry for your loss, Kwan.
Despite their differences,
the UNSC respected
the way that Jin Ha
stood up for himself
and the people of Madrigal.
Kwan, I'm not a politician.
I spend my time trying
to understand the aliens
that attacked your outpost.
Yours isn't the first planet
to face the Covenant,
and, unfortunately,
it won't be the last.
If we don't all join together...
I don't know how we're going
to stop them.
You could help us
do that.
What does that mean?
If you would upload a few words
to the other colonies,
just explaining what you saw,
the brutality of the Covenant,
the fact that the Spartans
are actually taking them on,
I think that it would go
a long way to putting aside
whatever these politicians
are bickering about
and helping us focus
on the real war.
My dad spent his life
trying to free us from you...
until the day of his murder.
How can you ask me to...
to go on camera and--?
-I understand. I'm not trying--
-No, no, no.
It's a great idea.
Yeah, let's do it.
What if I say the UNSC
sent a bunch of Spartans
to attack us.
That's not true.
They killed over
a hundred innocent people.
Children.
And then...
and then you kidnapped me
to force me to say
it was all the aliens.
Kwan, the entire encounter
was recorded.
You people can make video
look like anything.
We've seen your Spartan
propaganda broadcasts.
You think the Outer Colonies
don't see through that?
And when they hear
my version,
you can forget about unity
or whatever.
Those other colonies
are going to run from the UNSC
as fast as they can.
What is it you want?
Independence for Madrigal.
That's what my dad wanted.
So that's what I want.
Yeah.
[sighs]
Get some rest.
I'll see you on Reach.
[woman] Getting
a red light on hatch 4.
[woman 2] Commander Shepherd,
you are requested
at the Skillian Response Center.
[sobbing softly]
[John, over monitor]
Retrieving now.
[soft gasp]
Biometrics
are all over the map.
Body temperature is up.
It's up.
Lymphatics,
they're ignited.
Elevated activity
in his hypothalamus
and pineal glands.
Look, look.
The energy pulse is stimulating
his connective tissue.
All this from contact
with a piece of rock.
Has he said anything?
No.
How long until they're back?
-Better part of a day.
-Okay.
Sierra 1-1-7.
[computerized voice]
Connecting.
[over intercom]
Dr. Halsey. Status report.
Returning from Twenty-Three
Librae, Planet Madrigal,
with a single survivor.
Covenant disarmed,
one escapee.
And your neural lace metrics,
any anomalies?
[sighs]
I saw things...
when I touched the object.
What kind of things?
Woods.
A white dog.
A family.
A family?
That's what it felt like.
Okay.
John...
until we know more
about that object,
I'd like you to keep
your distance from it.
Copy that.
You've been through a lot, John.
So, whatever's happened,
you get yourself back here
and we will sort it out, okay?
[John]
Yes, ma'am.
-Sierra out.
-[intercom beeps off]
I need live updates every
ten minutes streamed to me,
and when he lands,
you bring him straight here.
Yes, ma'am.
Okay.
Please, open the door.
Please--
-[beeps]
-[computer] Identification.
Master Chief, Petty Officer,
John 1-1-7.
What are you doing?
Scanning the integrity
of all bio interfaces
for evidence
of abnormalities.
That your way of saying
you don't feel well?
Checking systems.
[computer pinging]
Yes.
You gonna live?
Hey.
There anything to eat
on this ship?
[equipment whirrs]
[indistinct chatter]
Heard you played politician
today with the rebel girl.
Dad, I tried.
I sucked up my pride,
and I really--
I gave it my best.
I believe you.
Selling Dr. Halsey's Spartans
to a rebel, of all people.
As if Halsey'd ever
do a thing to promote me.
-That's not entirely fair.
-Please don't. Don't defend her.
She's done nothing
but throw roadblocks in my way.
Halsey's always been
single-minded.
Work is the only thing
that matters.
I made my peace with that
a long time ago.
It's nothing personal.
"Nothing personal"
isn't a great excuse
when it's your mom.
[man] Blood, ocular fluid,
glandular extracts,
and bone samples
sent to external lab...
You know,
you are a lot like her.
[scoffs]
Ouch.
I mean that as a compliment.
Anyway...
I'm guessing the UNSC
isn't about to grant Madrigal
complete independence.
Mnh-mnh.
So what happens now,
to the girl?
That's what I came over here
to tell you.
Tell me what?
Kwan Ha was badly wounded
in the alien attack
on Madrigal.
Despite our best efforts,
she succumbed to her injuries.
I-I spoke to her,
and she was fine.
What--? What injuries?
Dad.
You didn't order an Article 72.
Came from up top.
I wanted you
to hear it from me.
Well, then you're okay
with this?
It's not about being okay.
No, it's about keeping
the deuterium flowing,
regardless of the cost.
-It is not that simple.
-It is that simple.
It's-it's an Article 72.
We're murdering
a teenage girl...
and I'm complicit.
We're in a war, Miranda.
The future of humanity--
What's the point
in saving humanity
if we're going to give up
our own?
Sometimes you have to make hard
choices to get good results.
Now who's sounding like Halsey?
You don't eat?
Didn't see anything I liked.
Yeah?
What is it you like?
Nuts. Bolts.
Microchips.
-That was a joke.
-Yeah, no, I get it.
Hilarious.
You ever take that thing off?
All of my diagnostic command
and control systems
run through here.
I need it.
Master Chief, huh?
You know we've actually met
before today.
When was this?
When you killed my mother.
She was at a meeting.
Outer Colonists getting together
to talk about how the UNSC
was stripping us
of all our natural resources.
But before they got
into all that,
you and three other
Spartans showed up,
responding to an insurrectionist
bomb threat.
But, see, that never made
much sense, because why would--?
Why would insurrectionists
blow up a meeting
for insurrectionists?
Yeah.
We were ordered
to eliminate the organizer.
And the orders changed.
To what?
The assembled were deemed
an imminent threat.
My mom seemed like
an imminent threat to you?
What I can see on the ground
may not reflect
the entirety
of the situation.
-What does that mean?
-Sometimes...
others know things I do not.
It ever occur to you that it
might work the other way around?
Then you question everything?
And someone told you
that's bad?
Of course they did.
It's funny, I...
I don't look at pictures
of my mom that often, but...
you...
you're everywhere.
Can't turn around without
staring at an uplink
about humanity's
best weapon.
[sighs]
[rapid computerized beeping]
What is your name?
Kwan Ha.
How much longer
are we stuck in here?
ETA is still several hours.
And then what?
That's still being
worked out.
[Halsey]
So, what's the problem?
Roll it back for her.
Yes, ma'am.
[overlapping chatter]
What's he doing?
Wait for it.
Captain, does Master Chief
know the girl is Article 72?
Of course. It would have been
communicated to him.
Dr. Halsey, what's wrong
with 1-1-7?
Nothing, it's just
a neurochemical glitch
caused by a power surge
to his prefrontal cortex.
It's not nothing.
Rather than execute the rebel
as ordered,
he has decided to kill
the video feed from his ship.
What's going on?
I think he's having memories.
What?
Of?
His parents.
I thought you'd sealed
those memories.
[Halsey] He's not even certain
that they're his memories.
For the moment,
they're just visions.
Then why violate procedure?
I don't know.
Not knowing why
a walking killing machine
is doing what it's doing
is a risk that cannot
be taken.
I agree completely,
which is precisely why
the Cortana system could prove--
There is no Cortana system,
Catherine.
No cloning, no Cortana.
Is that clear?
Now get your Spartan
under control.
-[door hisses open]
-What's happening?
Something is...
wrong.
I can't breathe.
What are you doing?
[technician]
Ship's oxygen levels dropping.
I need to...
Kwan.
Take down the oxygen
in 1-1-7's suit.
Don't drop the O2 below 40.
I want him unconscious,
-not dead.
-Yes, ma'am.
Can the girl survive this?
I thought you wanted her dead.
[alarm beeping]
[wheezes]
[alarm beeping continues]
-It's over there.
-Here.
It's holding at 40%.
He's unconscious.
[gasps]
I'm getting a report of access
to panel Alpha 1-6.
If he's unconscious, how come
he's opening panels in the ship?
-What's in A-1-6?
-Atmosphere controls.
-[air hissing]
-[John sighs]
[technician] Oxygen levels
are returning to normal.
What sort of weapons
is the ship carrying?
John is not going to fire on us.
I think it's safe to say
you don't know
what Master Chief is going to do
at this point.
[Keyes] Ship's flying on AI.
We have control.
I'll send an escort of Pelicans.
I need more than an escort,
Captain.
Put out the alarm.
Scramble everyone
to landing bay,
full squadron protocol.
Due respect,
we are talking about
our most important
military asset.
We are not taking any chances.
Let me investigate.
I'll speak to John,
and whatever influence
this object's--
Question one more order, Doctor,
and you can watch
from your lab.
[alarm blaring]
[soldier 1]
Come on! Let's go! Move!
-Move out!
-[soldier 2] Let's go! Let's go!
Move your ass out! Go!
Move, move, move!
[soldiers shouting]
Clear.
[Halsey, over intercom]
Silver team,
Master Chief
has been compromised
by the object you located
on Madrigal.
Because of this, he's no longer
able to comply with orders.
You've been dispatched
by Fleet Command
to neutralize him.
-I'm superseding those orders.
-[man] Move!
Whatever he's experiencing,
there are other
available solutions.
When that ship lands,
I want you to secure
and protect Master Chief
from anyone who actively
threatens his life,
whatever the circumstances.
Engage friendlies, ma'am?
If they go after Chief,
they're not friendlies.
Correct, Dr. Halsey?
Correct.
[engine powering up]
Kwan.
Don't move.
You're gonna need
to listen to me.
What did you do to me?
Stop messing
with that stuff.
UNSC changed the air mixture,
not me.
Why should I trust you?
I am trying to get control
of the flight.
I will kill you.
[breathing heavily]
This is Mark Six
Mjolnir armor.
The outer layer
is enhanced titanium.
You won't even dent it.
[air hisses]
If you want me dead...
you'll need to aim up here.
What just happened?
[rapid beeping]
I think he just took off
his helmet.
-What are you doing?
-Trying to help you.
If this ship lands,
they will remove you
and execute you.
They told you this?
And you just decided
to help me?
Why would a Spartan do that?
I don't know.
Get me thermal imaging
on the Condor.
[technician]
Right away.
So what now?
We need to work fast.
[Keyes] There's
a weapon signature on the girl.
Did your Spartan just give
an insurgent a rifle?
Green Deck, two minutes
till touchdown.
Two minutes!
[soldier]
Let's go! Let's go! Let's go!
[overlapping shouts]
Open ECAM panel two.
Disconnect the AI
autopilot fail-safe.
-Autopilot what?
-[John] ECAM panel two!
That's how we get control
of the ship.
-Rip out the cables to the FMS!
-Which cables?
I need to disconnect
the stabilizer servos
at the same time, otherwise
we lose complete control.
I can't! They're stuck!
Must work faster, Kwan!
I'm trying!
[soldier]
Go! Go! Go!
[indistinct shouts]
[grunts]
Shit!
[alarms beeping]
[powering down]
[computerized voice]
...now in manual mode.
You are now in manual mode.
[alarm beeping]
He's disabled the AI.
Flying manually, ma'am.
What are we waiting for?
I thought you had control.
I do. Hang on.
Captain...
This is Keyes.
Pulse the ship
before he can load
fire controls.
Knock it down!
[sharp grunt]
[loud crash]
[artifact clatters]
[solider]
Let's go! Move!
[breathing heavily]
[solider]
Move! Flanking starboard!
Halt! Cover me!
Ready!
[soldier]
Bravo Two, at the door!
[soldier 2]
Hold your line!
In your ranks!
Hold your section!
What do we do?
[panting]
[soldier]
Prepare to breach!
What do we do?
-All engines dead.
-No response.
Drop the girl.
And if he makes a move,
drop him too.
Shit.
Master Chief, please tell me
you have a plan.
[soldier]
Placing charges!
[beeping]
Master Chief!
[artifact clicking]
[energy flows]
[beeping]
[laughing]
-[Young John] Want to see?
-[mother] Of course.
[energy powers down]
[woman]
What just happened?
Debasement status?
[systems powering up]
A.I. is disengaged.
What did you just do?
[technician]
Switching to auxiliary power.
[Parangosky]
What was that?
[overlapping chatter]
[grunts]
[all shouting]
Strap in.
[end theme music playing]